Something almost beyond comprehension is happening to a girl on this street, in this
house…And a man has been sent for as a last resort. This man is The Exorcist.
The Exorcist is a horror film directed by William Friedkin.
When a mysterious entity possesses a young girl, her mother seeks
the help of two Catholic priests to save her life.
Chris MacNeil, played by Ellen Burstyn.
Regan MacNeil, played by Linda Blair.
Father Damien Karras, played by Jason Miller.
Father Lankester Merrin, played by Max von Sydow.
Lt. Bill Kinderman, played by Lee J. Cobb.
Father Joseph Kevin Dyer, played by William O'Malley.
The Exorcist is a 1973 American supernatural horror film directed by William Friedkin
from a screenplay by William Peter Blatty, based on his 1971 novel.
The film stars Ellen Burstyn, Max von Sydow, Jason Miller, and Linda Blair, and follows the demonic
possession of a young girl and the attempt to rescue her through an exorcism by two Catholic priests.
Blatty, who also produced, and Friedkin, his choice as
director, had difficulty casting the film.
Their choice of relative unknowns Burstyn, Blair, and Miller, instead of
major stars, drew opposition from executives at Warner Bros.
Principal photography was also difficult.
Many cast and crew were injured, some died, and
unusual accidents delayed shooting.
Production took twice as long as scheduled and cost almost three times the initial
budget; the many mishaps have led to a belief that the film was cursed.
The Exorcist was theatrically released in the United
States on December 26, 1973, by Warner Bros.
Reviews were mixed, but audiences waited in long lines during cold weather; the sold-out shows were even more profitable for Warner
Bros., who had booked it into those theaters under four-wall distribution rental agreements, a first for any major studio.
Some viewers suffered adverse physical reactions, fainting or vomiting to
shocking scenes such as a realistic cerebral angiography.
Many children were allowed to see the film, leading to charges that the Motion Picture Association of America (MPAA) had accommodated the
studio by giving the film an R rating instead of an X rating to ensure the troubled production its commercial success.
Several cities attempted to ban it outright or prevent children from attending.
At the end of its original theatrical run, the film grossed $193 million, and
has a lifetime gross of $441 million with subsequent re-releases.
The cultural conversation around the film helped it become the first horror film to be
nominated for the Academy Award for Best Picture, as well as nine others.
Blatty won Best Adapted Screenplay, while the sound engineers took Best Sound.
It has had several sequels and was the highest-grossing R-rated
horror film (unadjusted for inflation) until 2017's It.
The Exorcist significantly influenced pop culture, and it has been
included on lists of the greatest films ever made.
In 2010, the Library of Congress selected the film for preservation in the United States National
Film Registry as being "culturally, historically, or aesthetically significant".
The film explores themes of washington dc, usa, religion and
supernatural, exorcism, holy water, paranormal phenomena.
The tone is dark and intense.